托马斯-博林阁下 蒙亨利国王圣恩浩荡 钦赐为
Sir thomas boleyn, you are by order and permission of his majesty, king henry!
罗克福贵爵
Today created lord rochford.
起身 爵士
Arise my lord.
谢陛下
Majesty.
亨利-菲茨罗伊
Henry fitzroy.
亨利-菲茨罗伊 蒙亨利国王圣恩浩荡 钦赐为
Henry fitzroy, you are, by order and permissionf f his majesty, king henry,
里士满
today created duke of richmond.
萨莫塞特公爵
and of somerset,
兼诺丁汉伯爵
and earl of nottingham.
起身 殿下
Arise, your grace.
红衣主教沃尔西阁下到
His eminence, cardinal wolsey.
皇后殿下
Your majesty.
我见陛下的私生子获封公爵
I see his majesty's bastard son is made a duke.
是不是意味着他是陛下的继承人？
Does this mean he is next in rank to his majesty?
地位仅次于国王？
Next in line to the throne?
甚至在我女儿之上？
Above my daughter?
律法意义上来说是的
Yes. Technically.
他比其他人地位都高
He is set above all others,
除了… 嫡生王子
except for… a legitimate son.
陛下深爱我们的女儿
His majesty loves our daughter.
在很多场合都流露过这种爱意
He has shown it on many occasions.
难以相信他竟然让自己的私生子 凌驾于我们的女儿之上
I cannot believe he wishes to place his bastard child above her!
我也不相信…
I do not believe…
陛下…
that his majesty.
此举只是出自个人意愿
was personally responsible for this action.
毕竟
After all,
我们的女儿已经与罗马皇帝订婚
our daughter is engaged to the emperor.
原来王后娘娘未曾听说
Then your majesty has not heard.
罗马皇帝已经迎娶葡萄牙公主 伊莎贝拉为妻
The emperor has married princess isabella of portugal.
很显然他觉得等待您的女儿长大 并不值得
Apparently he decided it was not worth waiting for your daughter to grow up.
传言说他领悟到一个事实
And who is to say but perhaps he was influenced by the fact.
美丽的伊莎贝拉公主的嫁妆
that the beautiful isabella brought with her.
有一百万英镑
a dowry of 1 million pounds.
他违背了他的诺言
He broke his word.
我的王
My lord.
您示爱的赠品和暗示让我如此惶恐
How your tokens and signs of affection frighten me.
我何德何能成为您心目中的女神？
How can I be to you what you think me to be?
您清楚我只是一介布衣 无法与您的爱慕相配
You know I am a commoner and I think myself unworthy of your love.
陛下的馈赠和炽烈的诗句与眼神
Thither offer of it and the passion of your majesty's words and looks.
深深地触动了我的心和灵魂
touch both my heart and soul.
「您用如此繁多如此精致的礼物 取悦我
"You have flattered me with so many and such wondrous gifts."
「请允许我献上我的回馈信物
"Allow me to send you this token in return, "
「虽然微不足道
"small though it is."
「却代表了…
"And allow me to remain, "
「我所有的一切
"in all things, "
「永远爱慕您的仆人
"your everloving servant."
安「
"Anne."
殿下
Your grace.
妈妈
Mama!
亨利 现在听我说 你就要拥有你自己的府邸了
Now, henry, listen to me. You are going to own your own house now.
你会有很多的仆人 帮助你 照顾你
You'll have lots of servants to help you and look after you.
但你要答应我做个好孩子
But you must promise me to be a good boy.
对你身边的人体贴入微 仁慈宽厚
and thoughtful and kind to those around you.
即使你凌驾于他们之上
You may be set above them.
但如果你长成不可一世的样子 我会很伤心难过
but if I find you have grown too proud I will be sad and displeased.
是的 妈妈 我答应你
Yes, mama. I promise.
我也答应你尽我所能去看你
And I promise I'll come and see you as often as I can.
我也相信你的府邸会非常宏伟
And I'm sure your new house will be very grand!
我爱你 我的好儿子
I love you, my darling boy.
我爱你
I love you.
你觉得他们怀疑我吗？
Do you think they were suspicious? Ever?
他们当然怀疑过你
Of course they were suspicious!
难道你没有看见他的侍从们看你的眼神？
Didn't you see the way his servants looked at you?
不过他的儿子可是喜不自胜 我是说 国王陛下喜不自胜
But his son was overjoyed. I mean, his majesty was overjoyed.
毕竟 他苦等那座皇冠已经数年了
After all, he had waited many years for the crown.
老家伙在世时死拽着不放
The old man had hung on grimly.
这些不用你跟我说
You need not tell me about that!
我们该怎么办？
What are we going to do?
这还不够吗？
Isn't this enough?
不 哦 也是 也不是
No. Well, yes and no.
我们最终还是要回到英格兰
We shall come to england eventually.
嫁给我
Marry me.
什么？
What?
你听见了
You heard me.
嫁给我
Marry me.
我可怜的王妹
My poor sister.
的的确确
Indeed.
皇后的宝座才坐了几天 真是难以置信
To be made queen for just a few days. It seems incredible.
让人伤心欲绝
A tragedy.
她归来后服丧期间 务必受到舒适温暖的款待
Upon her return she is to be treated to every comfort and kindness, while she mourns.
至于陛下您的离婚大事
As to the great matter of your majesty's annulment.
我已与华翰主教筹建了一个教廷
I have set up an ecclesiastical court with archbishop warham.
以备商讨决策
to consider and decide on the matter.
一切都秘密进行 如蒙陛下恩准
It will meet in secret, if your majesty agrees.
确保他们做出正确的决定
Make sure they come to the right decision.
速战速决
Quickly.
我还有些纵深消息
I have some further news.
关于罗马皇帝的
About the emperor.
他已经释放了弗朗西斯国王
He has released king francis.
什么？
What?!
消息来源非常可信
I have it on good authority.
以什么条件释放的？
Under what terms?!
有待查实
I have yet to find out.
为什么不与我磋商？我们是盟国
Why wasn't I consulted? We're supposed to be allies!
他葫芦里卖的什么药？
What's he playing at?
告诉大使我要见他
Tell his ambassador I want to see him.
安 安
Anne! Anne!
安
Anne.
我要对我说一番话
I want to say something to you.
若你喜做我真实忠诚的情人和朋友
If it pleases you to be my true, loyal mistress and friend…
就献出你的身体和灵魂 都给我
to give yourself up to me, body and soul.
我保证待你为唯一的情人
I promise I'll take you as my only mistress.
我不会移情别恋
I won't have a thought or affection for anyone else.
若你同意做我的授爵情人
If you agree to be my maitresse en titre,
我保证只为你一个人效力
I promise I shall serve only you.
授爵情人？
Maitresse en titre?
您正式的情人？
Your official mistress?
是的
Yes!
你会得到你想要的一切
And you will have everything you need.
只要在我王权之内 都是你的 只要你开口
Everything within my power to give to you. It's yours, just ask.
怎么了？
What is it?
我造了什么孽 让您这样对我？
What have I done to make you treat me like this?
造孽？
Done?
我做错什么了？你说
What fault have I committed? Tell me!
你说
Tell me.
陛下我已决定将贞操献给我的丈夫
Your majesty I have already given my maidenhead into my husband's hands.
不管他是谁 只有他才能拥有
And whoever he is, only he will have it.
安…
Anne…
因为我清楚事情会怎样变坏
because I know how it goes otherwise.
我姐姐被大家称为「名妓」
My sister is called "the great prostitute" by everyone.
抱歉冒犯了你
I'm sorry if I offended you.
并非我本意
I did not mean to.
我袒露我的真心
I spoke plainly of my true feelings.
陛下
Your majesty.
- 陛下 - 开门
- Majesty. - Open the door!
快点
*****
玛丽 玛丽
Mary. Mary.
回你的房间 我随后就到
Go to your room. I will come later.
再次拜访啊 主教大人 您可真是日理万机
Another visit, your eminence!
殿下 好消息
Majesty, I have some good news.
既然国王陛下已经赐予领地给 皇子里士满公爵
Since his majesty has given his son, the duke of richmond his own establishment,
他深思熟虑之后觉得 他深爱的公主玛丽
he considers it only.
也应有此封赏
should also have hers.
愿闻其详
What do you mean?
陛下有意送给公主 威尔士边界的拉德洛城堡
His majesty intends to send the princess to ludlow castle in the welsh marches.
她将由萨利斯贝利夫人悉心照料
She will be under the care of lady salisbury,
做她的教侍
her lady governess.
她的私人老师费瑟斯顿爵士 也将陪同前往
Her tutor, dr. Fetherston will also accompany her,
随行的还有300名公主的家仆
along with 300 members of the princess's household.
我的女儿要离我远去了？
She is to be taken away from me?
非也 陛下赐予了她 一个公主真正的荣耀
No. His majesty is according her the true honours of a princess.
是你的诡计
This is your idea.
夫人 我常常担负莫须有的罪名
Madam, I am often accused of things that are not my fault or responsibility.
有些人惯于不明真相 不守真理就信口雌黄
Some people are always prone to speak evil without knowledge of the truth.
我深恐他们的行为玷污了 王后娘娘对我的看法
I fear they may have poisoned your majesty's mind against me.
你要夺走我的孩子
You are taking my child from me!
我的孩子
My child!
你把她从我身边夺去 就如同你曾把她从我子宫里夺去一样
You are tearing her from me, as if you were tearing her from my womb.
我只是奉陛下的命办事
I do as his majesty commands.
胡说
No.
你是我的仇人
You are my enemy.
殿下此言差矣
Your majesty is unfair.
从我眼前消失
Get out of my sight.
玛丽
Mary.
Mary!
至高至圣罗马帝国大使到
The ambassador of his highness the holy roman emperor.
门多萨爵士
Senor mendoza,
见到你我很不高兴
I am not pleased to see you.
陛下？
Majesty?
你的主子违背了他所有的诺言
Your master has broken all his promises.
他收了我们的钱 却反过来倒打一耙
He has taken our money but used it against us.
他同法兰西国王背着我密谋单方面和平
He has negotiated a separate peace with the king of france.
和教皇大人 却疏忽了他的朋友和同盟
and his holiness the pope while neglecting his friend and ally!
他没有守约
He has not kept faith.
查尔斯对我只有三言两语
Charles has nothing but words for me!
对别人却是签约立契
Deeds he keeps for others!
国王殿下不会背叛陛下 永远
The emperor would never betray your majesty. Never!
他敬您为皇叔…
He regards you as his uncle he.
狗屁皇叔
his fucking uncle!
我才多大？
How old am I?
陛下也当考虑到
Well, your highness must consider that you, yourself.
您自己并未尽责
may not always have kept to your obligations.
毕竟 我们只收到承诺中黄金数量的一半
After all, we received only half the amount of gold that was promised.
你的指责完全是荒谬
Your accusations are totally false!
不可接受
Unacceptable!
无论和人与我抵触 我都将还之于人
I will answer for my honourable conduct, whoever contradicts me!
滚
Leave.
罗彻福德阁下
My lord rochford.
是的 阁下
Yes, your honour.
国王殿下对您的升迁传达最热烈的祝贺
The emperor sends you his warmest congratulations on your elevation.
国王殿下为何关心我的升迁？
What does the emperor care about my elevation?
他愿在英格兰宫中结友并为之献惠
He cares to have friends at the english court and pays for the privilege.
他不已有朋友在其中吗？
Does he have many friends here already?
些许
Several.
你将与他们结识
You would know them.
而这友谊将得何惠？
And what does friendship pay?
每年一千克朗
1000 crowns a year.
我定会考虑殿下优裕的提案
I will certainly consider his highness's gracious offer.
阁下
Your grace.
大人
My lord!
你对西班牙国使感觉如何？
So how did you find the imperial ambassador?
令人心动
Stimulating.
的确如此
Indeed.
我觉得他是名极有原则的人
I find him a man of great principle.
的确如此
Indeed.
哈利路亚
Hallelujah.
的确是哈利路亚
Hallelujah indeed.
大人
My lord.
不必 我只是在赏曲
No, I was just listening.
是 我…
Yes. I…
你禀赋非常
you have such a talent.
奥菲斯恐怕也羡慕
Orpheus himself would be jealous, I think.
爵士
Sir.
日安 威廉爵士
Good day, sir william.
你们也日安
A very good day to you.
不觉这音乐动人吗？
Isn't the music divine?
是啊 非常同意
Yes, I quite agree.
失陪
Ladies.
Sir william.
不 乔治 求你 还给我
No, george! Please. Give it back!
我已将心献于你 而我渴望
I have given you my heart now I desire.
- 将身体也献于你 - 不要 拜托
- to dedicate my body to you. - Don't! Please.
由全身心爱你坚贞不移
Written by the hand of him who in heart, body and will is your loyal.
的奴仆亲笔
and most ensured servant,
H R 喔…
hr. Aw…
看看 他在H和R之间还画了颗心
and look! He's drawn a little heart between the lett h and R.
想象一下吧
Just imagine,
英格兰国王写信给我妹妹
the king of england writing to my little sister.
说愿做她的奴仆
promising to be her servant.
真是令人难以置信
It's incredible.
把信给我
Give me the letter.
他爱上你了
He's in love with you.
把信给我
Give the letter!
你没有爱上他 对吗？
You're not in love with him are you?
他要离婚？
He wants a divorce?!
这不是离婚
It's not a divorce.
国王要废除婚约
The king wants an annulment on the grounds.
以他本就不该结婚为由
that he was never married in the first place.
娶他哥哥的妻子已经触犯了
By marrying his brother's wife he has offended the laws.
天条凡法
of both god and man.
他只是想得到承认
He simply wants that recognized.
教皇特许了他娶凯瑟琳
The pope gave him a dispensation to marry katherine!
他的确特许了
Indeed he did.
这点无可质疑
No one denies it.
但国王认为他对上帝所负责任 应该比他对教皇所负的要多
But the king feels more beholden to god than he does to the pope.
他的良知深受谴责并为之触痛
His conscience is genuinely stricken, and tender.
他违背了上帝的旨意
He has disobeyed god's injunction.
教皇无论如何言语如何行动 也改不了这一事实
and there's nothing his holiness can say or do that can alter that fact.
教皇是上帝在世间的代言人
The pope is god's representative on earth.
他为上帝的口舌
He speaks for him.
哦 拜托了 托马斯 你在装什么？
Oh, come, come thomas. What are you pretending?!
国王一直离婚的
Kings get divorced all the time.
教皇也总能找到借口
And popes always find an excuse.
我知道你是理想主义者 但你也不是傻子
I know you're an idealist but you're not stupid!
如果亨利要废除婚约谁能拦住他？
If henry wants an annulment who's to stop him?
好吧 你就事论事
Alright. You talk of fact.
我也就和你就事论事
Let me give you a fact.
阿拉贡的凯瑟琳不光是名伟大的皇后 是伟大先王的千金
Catherine of aragon is not only a great queen and the daughter of great kings,
她也受全国百姓的爱戴
she is also immensely popular throughout the whole of the country.
国王只为治愈良知而抛弃她也是上帝所不啻的
God forbid that the king should abandon her just to ease his own conscience.
我不觉得英格兰人民会原谅他
I don't think the english people would ever forgive him.
她知情吗？
Does she know yet?
她知道不知道？
（朗伯斯教堂）
在钉着救世主的十字架下
Behold the cross on which hung the savior of the world.
朗伯斯的善人们
Good people of lambeth.
在这基督受难日 皇后陛下将为贫穷
On this good friday the queen's majesty will distribute alms to you unfortunate.
却忠心耿耿的人们发放救济
but true and loyal subjects of their majesties…
以圣灵与慈爱的名义
in the christian spirit of charity and love.
上帝保佑你
Bless you.
还有你
And you.
上帝与你同在
God be with you.
也与你同在
*****
保持信仰
In good faith.
陛下 我恳求您 救救我
Your majesty, I beseech you, help me.
上帝保佑你
God bless you.
不要害怕 你是上帝的子民
Do not be afraid. You are god's child.
上帝保佑
Bless you.
想验验我们的货吗？
Wanna see our business?
抱歉 不要
Sorry, love.
亲爱的威廉
My dear william.
查尔斯 欢迎回来 见到你真好
Charles, welcome back, good to see you.
你也是 来 坐下 喝一杯
You too. Come, sit down, have a drink.
我不明白 为何此处？
I just don't understand. Why here?
我们都等着你回宫
We've been expecting you back at court.
国王尚安？
How is the king?
焦虑的等待着
Anxiously awaiting his sister.
去安抚他悲伤的妹妹
to share her grief.
我们结婚了
We're married.
什么？
What?
她… 和我
She… and me!
我们结婚了
We're married.
你和… ？
You and…?
是的
Yes.
来了 先生们
Here you are, sir.
你得告诉他
You have to tell him.
你得告诉国王
You have to tell the king.
我得告诉他？为什么是我去告诉他？
I have to tell him? Why do I have to tell him?
因为从你口中听到会好些
Because it'd be better coming from you.
你怎么了 查尔斯？魂丢了吗？
What's the matter, charles? Have you lost your nerve?
这可不是说笑
This is no laughing matter.
那你为什么要这么做？
Then why did you do it?
你了解我的
You know me.
我有时候就是不思考
I don't always think.
不 你思考
Yes you do.
只不过不是用脑袋
Just not with your head! Huh?
亨利？你…
Henry? You.
凯瑟琳 我有话要对你说
katherine, I have something to tell you.
据我看来 我们的婚姻已经结束
As far as I'm concerned our marriage is at an end.
事实上… 对于从未开始的事情也没有结束可言
Actually… there is no need to end something which has never been.
你我从未真正结婚
You and I were never truly married.
那是对圣经的误读
There was a misunderstanding of scripture.
和对圣典的滥用
and a papal misapplication of canon law.
说真的我…
It's true I…
我以前对此一无所知但…
I did not know about these things before but…
钻研之后我对其明朗起来
but it has been brought to light by learned opinion.
并深深挫伤了我的良知
And it weighs down my conscience.
我不得不完完全全放弃你
It has forced me to give up your bed and board once and for all.
你唯一可做的选择是住到何处
All that remains is for you to choose where to live.
然后尽快搬迁
and to retire there as quickly as possible.
我向你发誓
I swear to you.
这都是最好的打算
all will be done for the best.
尊敬的各位阁下…
Your grace, my lords…
我想你们已知晓我们为何再此密会
I believe you know why we are gathered here, in private.
我们奉陛下之令在此
We are here at his majesty's bidding.
陛下要求调查
His majesty has requested an inquiry.
他与阿拉贡的凯瑟琳的婚约之性质
into the nature of his marriage to catherine of aragon,
为了安抚他的良知 治愈他的灵魂
for the tranquility of his conscience and the health of his soul.
因利未记中有言：
For as it says in leviticus:
「人若娶弟兄之妻
"If a man shall take his brother's wife,
这本是污秽的事
it is an impurity.
羞辱了他的弟兄
He has covered his brother's nakedness,
二人必无子女「
they shall be childless."
阁下们 倘若此刻在我们之间
Now, if my lords, we are able to agree between ourselves.
能同意这婚姻原本并非合法
that the marriage was, in fact, never legal.
是违背了圣典与教会法则
and was proceeded with against both canon and ecclesiastical law.
国王陛下已深深忏悔然深信与其
as his majesty, to his great regret, has come to believe.
那么我就理解为
then it is my understanding.
作为教皇使节
that, as papal legate,
我自己有权废除这起婚姻
I myself have the power and authority to dissolve and end it.
当然我非常愿意
But of course I would be grateful.
听听各位大人对此事的看法
to hear the opinions of your lordships' on this great matter.
阁下？
Your grace?
我倾向于同意主教阁下的观点
I am inclined to agree with your eminence,
尽管在知晓详情前我保留看法
though I reserve judgment until I have heard all opinion.
费舍二阁下
My lord fisher.
在我看来国王没有丝毫过失 丝毫没有
I see no merit in the king's case, so expressed. None whatsoever.
即使国王的婚姻上有障碍
If there was any obstacle to the king's marriage.
也已被教皇的赦免令消除
then it was overcome by the pope's dispensation.
因此婚姻当为合法
The marriage was therefore legal.
而主教大人您也知道 教会是不允许离婚的
and as your eminence knows, divorce is disallowed by the church.
我的观点就是这样
That is my opinion.
主人
Madam.
索尔兹伯里夫人来了
Lady salisbury's here.
陛下
Your majesty.
我带您的千金来道别
I have brought your daughter to say goodbye.
我的宝贝
My baby.
陛下大可安心
Your majesty must be reassured.
我们会好好照顾公主 以符合她的身份
The princess will be well taken care of, as befitting her station.
我们会将她身心造诣定时禀报于您
You will be sent regular reports of her health and accomplishments.
当然您也可在巡游时探访她
And naturally you will visit her during the course of your majesty's progresses.
一定要让她悉心习乐
You must make sure she practices her music.
她在音乐上有天资
She has a great facility for music.
女儿你要坚强 记住你的身份
BE STRONG MY DAUGHTER, REMEMBER WHO YOU ARE.
卡斯蒂亚的费迪南德与伊莎贝拉的后裔
THE DECEENDENT OF ISABELLA AND FERDINAND OF CASTILLE.
英格兰国王的独女
THE ONLY DAUGHTER OF THE KING OF ENGLAND.
要坚强 要踏实 然后总有一天…
BE STRONG, AND BE TRUE AND ONE DAY…
总有一天你会成为女王
ONE DAY YOU WILL BE QUEEN.
知道了 妈妈
Yes, mama.
他内疚吗？
Is he sorry?
他懊悔吗？
Does he repent it?
告诉我 他有没有乞求我的宽恕？
Tell me! Does he beg my forgiveness?
陛下您应该了解他的
Your majesty knows his grace.
你是说他没有吗？
You mean he does not?!
传我妹妹进来
Send in my sister.
你未着黑色
You are not wearing black.
没有 陛下
No, your majesty.
但你应该服丧
But you are in mourning.
你的丈夫死了
Your husband is dead.
我说你的丈夫死了
I said your husband is dead!
他还活着
He's alive!
我的丈夫还活着
My husband is alive.
我没有准许你下嫁布兰顿
I gave you no permission to marry brandon.
也永远不会准许
Nor would I ever!
您许诺过我 我可以自由选择
You gave me your promise! I was free to choose.
我没有许诺过 是你搞错了
I made no promise! You are mistaken!
你还敢直视我？
How dare you look at me?!
我是你的王 是你的主子 不是你的哥哥
I am your lord and master not your brother!
你们两个将被逐出宫廷
You are both banished from court.
你在伦敦的住所将被剥夺
You will relinquish your london houses.
我要你从我眼前消失
You will remove yourself from my sight.
你明白了吗？
Do you understand?
遵命…
Yes…
陛下
your majesty.
还有 玛格丽特？
And margaret?!
何事？
What?
我还没决定是否该砍掉你床伴的头
I have yet to decide whether to make your bedmate a head shorter.
说你想要…
Say yes.
说你想要
你已为人夫
You're married.
又如何？
So?
因此…
So…
为什么拒绝我？
why deny me?
我不爱你
I do not love you.
仅仅如此吗？
Is that all?
对我来说 是的
For me. Yes.
你是如此的美丽 汤姆
You're so beautiful, tom.
你贵为主子
You're a lord.
我又算什么
What am I?
一个天才
A genius.
什么事？
What is it?
有包裹送到 陛下
A parcel, your majesty.
谁送来的
Who is it from?
安-博林女士
The lady anne boleyn.
有一个女人站在甲板上的船 船代表了什么？
A ship with a woman on board. What is a ship?
船代表了「保护」
A ship is protection,
犹如方舟保护着诺亚
like the ark that protected noah.
那么钻石呢？
The diamond?
「玫瑰传奇」里面是怎么说的
What does it say in the roman de la rose?
「一颗如钻石般坚固的心
"A heart as hard as a diamond,
忠贞不移…
"steadfast…"
恒久不变「
"never changing."
她就是钻石
She is the diamond.
而我就是那艘船
and I am the ship.
她应允了
She says yes!
弗朗西斯国王迫切的想和 陛下您修好
King francis is eager for a rapprochement with your majesty.
他因新罗马皇帝对您弃信忘义 的行为感到厌恶
He is disgusted at the treacherous behaviour of the emperor towards you.
他本人也因此行为深受其害
behaviour he knows only too well having suffered it himself at first hand.
并且提议与您建立真诚而长期的友谊
and offers you instead a true and lasting friendship.
的确如此
It is true,
新罗马帝国皇帝背叛了我们
the emperor has betrayed us.
或许他从一开始就没有以诚相待
Perhaps he was never sincere in the first place.
他甚至还有亲信戍守宫廷
Even so, he still has friends at court.
什么朋友？
Which friends?
我手下的探子截到这封信
My agents intercepted this letter.
由皇后所写的信
The letter is from the queen.
她询问新罗马皇帝为何 未能多些写信给她
She asks why the emperor doesn't write to her more often.
并且许诺 一如既往的做他真诚
And promises, as always, to be his true.
而卑微的仆人
and humble servant.
他的仆人
His servant.
却不是我的仆人
not mine.
跟法国大使说
Tell the french ambassador.
我们有与弗朗西斯国王 修好的意图
that we are in the mood for a rapprochement with king francis.
让他派代表过来
Tell him to send delegates.
让我们联手与圣罗马帝国抗衡
Let us be allies against this emperor.
我的女士
My lady.
我恳求得到你的处女之身
I lay claim to your maidenhead.
我要向您许诺：
And I make you this promise:
我们成婚之时 我会为您生下子裔
When we are married, I will deliver you a son.
不
No.
我已经珍惜你的处女之身 耐心等待到新婚之夜
I shall honour your maidenhead until we are married.
为了爱 何事我不可为？
No less can I do for love.
哦 我的爱人
Oh my love.
爱…
Love…
日复一日您让我领略
and by daily proof you shall me find,
您的爱之深 惜之切
to be to you both loving and kind.
我恨你
I hate you!
你说过一切都没事 你说他会相信你
You said it would be alright! You said he would believe you!
那是你说的 那是你所保证的
That's what you said! That's what you promised!
看在上帝仁爱的份上 我的妻
For the love of god, wife!
别叫我妻子
Don't call me wife.
我不想做你的妻子 我恨你
I don't want to be your wife. I hate you!
不 你不恨我
No, you don'T.
是的 我恨你
Yes, I do.
要不是因为你 我依旧还是葡萄牙的皇后
If it weren't for you I would still be the queen of portugal.
现在我成了什么？
And now what am I?
你喝多了 你在犯傻
You are drunk and you are foolish!
亨利会原谅我们 他不过是在维护自己的尊严
Henry will forgive us. He is just standing on his pride.
我们只不过伤害了他的虚荣心 相信我
We just wounded his vanity. Believe me.
哼
Huh.
为什么我该相信你？
Why should I?
真不知道你是真的勇敢
I don't know if you're really brave.
还是该死的蠢到家
or if you're just a fucking fool.
我也不知道
Neither do I.
哦 上帝
Oh god…
谢谢你 爱丽丝
thank you, alice.
我知道你和沃尔西谈过
I know you've talked to wolsey.
我也知道你并不赞同我要做的事情
And I know you do not approve of what I am trying to do.
违背了你的良知
It's against your conscience.
我并不会试图改变你的想法
And I'm not gonna try and change your mind.
不管怎样 这一招都是不可行
That's unlikely, in any case.
但是我需要你明白 托马斯
But I need you to understand, thomas.
我要跟你解释
I need to explain.
我一直和我的兄嫂住在一起
I have been living with my brother's wife.
我渐渐意识到他们的婚姻 言正其实
and I have come to believe their marriage was consummated.
如果真得如此
If that is true,
那么我一直都活在罪孽之中
then I have been living in sin.
你能体会那种感受吗 托马斯？
Can you understand what that feels like, thomas?
那就是为何我让主教大人验证此事
That is why I asked the cardinal to examine the matter.
但如果能证明教皇的安排 并无差池该怎么办？
But what if it can be proved that the pope's dispensation was valid.
那样就无罪孽可言
and that there was no sin?
那么我就是人世间最幸福的男人
Then I shall be the happiest man alive.
我将满心欢喜的与凯瑟琳携手终老
I shall be content to live with catherine until the end of my days.
等等
Wait.
我再次问您
I ask you again.
如果国王如此饱受良心的谴责
if the king is so troubled by his conscience,
为什么要等到现在才提出这个问题？
why has he waited so long to bring this matter to a head?
出于他对皇后的爱 他一直都在自我否认
Because of his love for the queen, he has denied the truth to himself.
但是她无法为他产下子裔 这就是证据
But her failure to produce a living son, is proof of it!
他想再婚？
Then he wants to remarry?
如果他的婚姻被注销无效 那么 是的 他会再婚
If his marriage is annulled, then yes I am certain he will remarry,
从而生下继位者
in the hope of producing an heir.
他已经有继位者
He has an heir!
我一刻也无法相信
I do not believe for a moment.
英格兰人民会认同私生子 为合法继位人
that the english people will accept his bastard son as a legitimate heir.
连国王也不会认同
and nor does the king!
他有一个名正言顺的女儿
He has a legitimate daughter!
各位大人们
My lords,
英格兰历史上已经充斥了那些
english history is littered with the tragedies.
传位给女儿的王者悲剧
of those who have tried to pass on their crown to a daughter!
那么…
Then…
他可否已经有新妻子的人选
he has a new wife in mind?
是的 他有意娶一女子
He has a mind to take one, yes.
下流
It stinks!
我认为你还是小心言语 大人
I think you should be careful, my lord.
你也该注意言行
As should you!
主教大人 拥有一间图书馆的好处之一
One of the great advantages of having a library, your eminence,
就是藏书万卷
is that it is full of books.
其中一些书里记录着神法
And some of these books contain ecclesiastical law.
根据那些书的内容 你无权干预此事
And according to those books you have no authority to judge this matter.
此事只能由教皇
It is for the pope alone.
或是由他亲典的人处理
it is for the pope alone or those whom he appoints.
主教大人 这样看来 您已经超越了自己的职权
It seems that in this case, your eminence, your reach has exceeded your grasp!
我已经邀请法国代表 来陛下的皇宫拜访
So, I have invited a french delegation to visit your majesty's court,
讨论两国联合
to discuss a new treaty,
共同与新罗马帝国拒绝合作 咄咄逼人而抗衡的新条约的事宜
binding us together in the face of the emperor's intransigence and aggression.
很好 非常好
Good. Excellent.
既然新罗马皇帝诋毁了 与玛丽公主的婚约
And since the emperor has reneged on his promise to marry your daughter,
或许从政治角度考虑
it could perhaps be politic.
我们应该重新考虑将玛丽公主下嫁法国皇太子一事
to resurrect her betrothal to the dauphin.
如果皇太子已经有了婚约 那就应该考虑弗朗西斯国王
Or if the dauphin has already promised, perhaps to the duke of orleans,
最年幼的儿子奥尔良公爵为人选
king francis's youngest son.
你的秘密会议进行如何？
And what of your secret sessions?
他们可否有所定夺？
Have they come to a decision?
要等到何事才能解除我的婚姻？
How soon can I expect my annulment?
陛下不该多虑 但是 呃…
Your majesty should not be concerned but uh…
我们还未能达成共识
we were not able to come to a conclusion.
未能？
Not able?
此事可为难事
The matter is a complex one.
真的？何以？
Really? How?
请赎鄙人多虑 我认为已经将此事 通报给教皇圣人克莱蒙
It is my considered opinion that we should apply to his holiness, pope clement.
由他来定夺
for a ruling on this matter.
陛下您一直深得其爱 我敢肯定他定会随了您的心愿
Since he loves your majesty I am certain he will rule in your favour.
哦 我希望如此
Oh, I hope so.
我当然希望如此
I certainly do hope so.
看在你的份上
For your sake.
一眼就能认出法国人来
You can always tell the french.
哦 是的 那群小白脸
Oh, yes. The ponces.
他们做过的最聪明的事 就是买通沃尔西
They never did anything so clever as giving wolsey a pension.
他从未让他们失望
He's never failed them.
我们必须静观其向
We must wait and see.
当时机之轮运转到顶峰之时
When the wheel of fortune has reached its zenith,
事态发展的方向就只有一个
there is only one way for it to go.
嗯-哼
Mm hmm.
让路 让路
Move aside! Out of my way!
我带来了最重要的消息
I bring most important news!
陛下 罗马已经被攻下
Your majesty! Rome has been sacked!
让他过来
Let him through!
陛下 赎我给你带来最可怕和不幸的消息
Your majesty, I bring most terrible and calamitous news.
罗马已经被德国和西班牙的圣罗马帝国雇佣兵攻下
Rome has been captured and sacked.
并洗劫一空
by the german and spanish mercenaries of the emperor.
他们抢掠并侮辱了那里的教会
They have plundered and befouled its churches,
摧毁了圣徒遗物及圣宝
destroyed its relics and holy treasures,
折磨并杀害了几千名传教士
tortured and killed thousands of its priests.
教皇圣人呢？
What of his holiness?
教皇被囚禁在圣天使堡
The pope is a prisoner in the castel sant'angelo.
他成了新罗马帝国皇帝的监下囚？
He is the emperor's prisoner?
是的
Yes.
布朗特女士
Lady blount.
他染上了汉热病
He caught the sweating sickness.
我们无能为力
There was nothing we could do.
今早他就说不舒服
He complained this morning of feeling ill.
晚间时 就已经归西了
By this evening he was in the hands of god.